Umme Aymun Siddiqua

Chittagong, Bangladesh

💌 aymun.cse@gmail.com | 🚱 aymun.netlify.app | 🖸 aymun | in umme-aymun-siddiqua | 🔰 @uasdqa

Research Interests

My research interests lie in the areas of natural language processing, social computing, multimodal opinion mining, and multilingual learning. Research topics that I worked on include detecting stance, hate speech, identify informative tweets in crisis events, memotion and sentiment analysis from social media content.

Education

Toyohashi University of Technology

M.Eng. in Computer Science and Engineering

• Thesis: "Stance Detection on Microblogs Using Syntactic Tree Kernels and Deep Neural Networks."

International Islamic University Chittagong

B.Sc. IN COMPUTER SCIENCE AND ENGINEERING

• Thesis: "Combining a Rule-based Classifier with Ensemble of Feature Sets and Machine Learning Techniques for Sentiment Analysis on Microblog."

Toyohashi, Japan September 2019

Chittagong, Bangladesh

August 2016

Work Experience _____

Asian University for Women

INSTRUCTOR IN COMPUTER SCIENCE

• Teach Courses, Assess Students' Works, Curriculum Development, and Evaluate Placement Tests.

TEACHING ASSISTANT IN HARVARD'S CS50 COURSE

• Conduct Lab Class, Problem Sets Discussion, and Assist Students.

COURSES TEACH

- Introduction to Computing and Programming
- Structured Programming Language C
- High-level Programming Language Python
- CS50's Introduction to Computer Science by Harvard University

Chittagong, Bangladesh January 2020 - Present

Research Experience _____

Asian University for Women

MENTOR AT AUW AI SOCIETY

• Advising Undergraduate Students Research.

Chittagong, Bangladesh

September 2021 - Present

Tovohashi University of Technology

GRADUATE RESEARCH STUDENT AT KDE LAB

• Conducted Research for M.Eng. Degree, Supervised by Professor Masaki Aono (PhD).

Toyohashi, Japan October 2017 - September 2019

Scholarships and Awards _____

INTERNATIONAL ACCOLADES

2019	The KDDI Foundation Scholarship for Master's Degree	Toyohashi, Japan
2017-2019	Monbukagakusho Honors Scholarship for Master's Degree	Toyohashi, Japan
2018, 2019	Research Assistantship Award at KDE Lab	Toyohashi, Japan

NATIONAL ACCOLADES

2014-2016 Undergraduate Academic Excellence Scholarship for Bachelor's Degree 2015 3rd Place, Awarded in the Software Development Competition at IIUC Tech Fest Project: Electronic Health Record (EHR) System with Symptom based Disease Prediction

Feature to Improve the Healthcare in Bangladesh.

Chittagong, Bangladesh Chittagong, Bangladesh

Publications

JOURNAL ARTICLES

- Abu Nowshed Chy, Umme Aymun Siddiqua, and Masaki Aono, Exploiting Transfer Learning and Hand-Crafted Features in a
 Unified Neural Model for Identifying Actionable Informative Tweets, Journal of Information Processing, Vol.29, pp.16-29, January
 2021.
- Umme Aymun Siddiqua, Abu Nowshed Chy, and Masaki Aono, Tweet Stance Detection using Multi-Kernel Convolution and Attentive LSTM Variants, IEICE Transactions on Information and Systems (IEICE TOIS), Vol.E102-D, No.12, pp.2493-2503, December 2019.

CONFERENCES/WORKSHOPS

• Abu Nowshed Chy, **Umme Aymun Siddiqua**, and Masaki Aono, A Neural Network Model to Identify the Crisis-related Actionable Informative Tweets for Disaster Management, *Proceedings of the 2020 IEEE Region 10 Symposium (TENSYMP)*, 5-7 June 2020, Dhaka, Bangladesh.

Best Paper Award (as a co-author)

- **Umme Aymun Siddiqua**, Abu Nowshed Chy, and Masaki Aono, Tweet Stance Detection Using an Attention based Neural Ensemble Model, *Proceedings of the 2019 Conference of the North American Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics:* Human Language Technologies (NAACL-HLT 2019), ACL, 2-5 June 2019, Minneapolis, Minnesota, USA.
- Umme Aymun Siddiqua, Abu Nowshed Chy, and Masaki Aono, Stance Detection on Microblog Focusing on Syntactic Tree Representation, 3rd International Conference on Data Mining and Big Data (DMBD 2018), Springer, 17-22 June 2018, Shanghai, China.
- **Umme Aymun Siddiqua**, Abu Nowshed Chy, and Masaki Aono, Combining a Rule-based Classifier with Ensemble of Feature Sets and Machine Learning Techniques for Sentiment Analysis on Microblog, *International Conference on Computer and Information Technology (ICCIT 2016)*, IEEE, 18-20 December 2016, Dhaka, Bangladesh.
- **Umme Aymun Siddiqua**, Abu Nowshed Chy, and Masaki Aono, Combining a Rule-based Classifier with Weakly Supervised Learning for Twitter Sentiment Analysis, *International Conference on Innovations in Science, Engineering and Technology (ICISET 2016)*, IEEE, 28-29 October 2016, Chittagong, Bangladesh.
- Abu Nowshed Chy, **Umme Aymun Siddiqua**, and Masaki Aono, CSECU_KDE_MA at SemEval-2020 Task 8: A Neural Attention Model for Memotion Analysis, *Proceedings of the 14th International Workshop on Semantic Evaluation (SemEval 2020)*, ACL, 13-14 September 2020, Barcelona, Spain.
- Umme Aymun Siddiqua, Abu Nowshed Chy, and Masaki Aono, KDEHatEval at SemEval-2019 Task 5: A Neural Network Model for Detecting Hate Speech in Twitter, *Proceedings of the 13th International Workshop on Semantic Evaluation (SemEval 2019)*, ACL, 6-7 June 2019, Minneapolis, Minnesota, USA.
- Abu Nowshed Chy, Umme Aymun Siddiqua, and Masaki Aono, Neural Networks and Support Vector Machine based Approach
 for Classifying Tweets by Information Types at TREC 2018 Incident Streams Task, Proceedings of the 27th Text REtrieval Conference
 (TREC 2018), NIST, 14-16 November 2018, Maryland, USA.

Presentations

AT CONFERENCES

- Poster presentation at NAACL-HLT 2019, Minneapolis, Minnesota, USA.
- Poster presentation at SemEval 2019, Minneapolis, Minnesota, USA.
- Oral presentation at DMBD 2018, Shanghai, China.
- Oral presentation at ICCIT 2016, Dhaka, Bangladesh.
- Oral presentation at ICISET 2016, Chittagong, Bangladesh.

Skills

Programming Languages

Programming Languages C, C++, R, Java, JavaScript, Python, Matlab

Frameworks & Libraries IDE Experiences

Keras, Tensorflow, Scikit-learn, NLTK, Gensim, PyTorch, Hugging Face Codeblocks, Visual Studio, Eclipse, PyCharm, RStudio, Jupyter, Atom, LaTeX

Certifications Deep Learning Specialization by DeepLearning.Al

Natural Language Processing Specialization by DeepLearning.Al Python for Everybody Specialization by University of Michigan

IT Training Industrial Training on Software Development

Institution: Scorpion Corporation, Chittagong.

Projects _

TITLES

- Electronic Health Record (EHR) System with Symptom based Disease Prediction Feature To Improve The Healthcare In Bangladesh
- Student Information Management and Result Processing System
- Online Banking System (Transaction Part)
- Social Networking Blog

TOOLS USED

• HTML, XHTML, CSS, JavaScript, PHP, AJAX, ¡Query, ERD, MySQL.

Languages _

- English Full Professional Proficiency
- Bangla Native or Bilingual Proficiency
- Japanese Elementary Proficiency

Co-curricular Activities

ASSISTANT GENERAL SECRETARY OF THE COMPUTER CLUB, IIUC

March 2015 - February 2016

- Organized IIUC Tech Fest 2014, 2015.
 - Events: Programming Contest, Software Development, Idea Generation,
 Tech Quiz, Debate Competition, Project Show, Robo Fight, and Poster Design.

PROGRAMMING CONTEST SECRETARY OF THE COMPUTER CLUB, IIUC

March 2013 – February 2015

• Arranged Inter University Programming Contest 2013, 2014, and 2015.

VOLUNTEER AT DIVISIONAL SCIENCE OLYMPIAD

January 2015

• Set Up and Ensured the Event Became Successful.

Travel History _____

• United States

June 2019 June 2018

China

October 2017 - September 2019

• Japan

References _

Available Upon Request.